Whiting, Indiana: Generational Memory 1991-1993 ohrc102
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
- Marcisz, John J., March 3, 1992; 91-152; Bodnar, John; 65 pages; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 129 minutes; index
  John J. Marcisz, born on December 4, 1913, discusses his parents' emigration from Poland, his childhood in Whiting, Indiana, and the emphasis on discipline and Catholic values that characterized his youth. He speaks of his father's years at Standard Oil, and the health problems, including black lung, that his father experienced as a result of the poor working conditions that defined his job as a still cleaner. Mr. Marcisz describes the ethnic diversity of Whiting and hypothesizes that few African-Americans lived in the area until recently because of the community's racism. He also recalls playing the sousaphone and trombone in Father Lach's traveling band when he was in high school.
  Arizona; Dreamland Villa, Arizona; 1955 Standard Oil fire; African-Americans; Catholicism; child discipline; discrimination; ethnic diversity; family values; Great Depression; local politics; pensions; racism; still cleaning; unions; working conditions; Standard Oil Company; Marcisz, Joseph; Marcisz, Mary
- Massoels, Richard, December 14, 1992; 91-176; Dabertin, David; 17 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 35 minutes; index
  Richard Massoels discusses his family and their Slovak ancestry, and emphasizes the importance of family, which he believes to be deteriorating in modern America due to such phenomena as the increased divorce rate. In addition, he recalls his education in Whiting, Indiana, the values he grew up with, and he describes his life in Whiting.
  child discipline; family values; AMOCO; Midway Airlines; St. John the Baptist Elementary School
- Mattingly, Betty L., November 15, 1990; 91-009; Dabertin, David; 23 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 109 minutes; index
  Betty L. Mattingly discusses her parents, growing up with ten brothers and sisters in a two bedroom house, and the discipline that characterized her youth. She describes her employment history and goes on to speak about her role in the United Citizens Association, created in response to the threat of Calumet College draining George Lake, sand mining it, and turning it into a land-fill.
  George Lake, Indiana; Robertsdale, Indiana; Wolf Lake, Indiana; child discipline; ecological activism; ethnic diversity; family values; George Lake drainage; pollution; prostitution; AMOCO; Calumet College; United Citizens Association; Christian, Ray
- Mattingly, Betty L., April 8, 1992; 91-160; Berry, Chad; 27 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index
  Born in 1933, Betty L. Mattingly describes the hard lives of her parents, how they met, and the value they placed on education. In addition, she discusses her extended family, including her mother's relationship with her many brothers and sisters, and their lives, careers, and current whereabouts.
  Tennessee; poverty; Christian; Christian, Elsie Mary
- McNinch, Estela, February 25, 1992; 91-148; Berry, Chad; 35 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 67 minutes; index
  Estela McNinch, born in July of 1964, discusses her parents' move from Texas and Mexico to Whiting, Indiana, the discipline she recalls from her childhood and adolescence, and her memories of her youth in Whiting, in general. She speaks of her high school class and the direction of the lives of some of her classmates. In addition, Mrs. McNinch, a Mexican American herself, comments on the role and experiences of Mexican-Americans in Whiting, and of diversity and discrimination in the town.
  discrimination; divorce; ethnic diversity; family values; hillbillies; Mexican-Americans
- Miller, Victoria, February 5, 1991; 91-013; Klemm, Verda; 33 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 98 minutes; index; photograph of interviewee
  Victoria Miller, born in December of 1919, discusses her Slovak and Hungarian background, her youth in Whiting, Indiana, which was characterized by her suffering of acute eczema, and the trials of life with an alcoholic and often abusive father. She speaks of her life, marriage, and children in this ethnically diverse community. In addition, she describes her interest and participation in handwriting analysis, community theater, and healthy eating.
  Whiting, Indiana; alcoholism; community theater; domestic abuse; eczema; ethnic diversity; family values; handwriting analysis; healthy eating; Marriage; AMOCO; Marion Theater Guild; The Patchworks; Kennedy, John Fitzgerald; Kennedy, Ted
- Mores, Mary R., April 30, 1992; 91-165; Bodnar, John; 37 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 95 minutes; index
  Born in 1924, Mary R. Mores discusses her Czechoslovakian ancestry, her parents, grandparents, and siblings, and her youth and life in Whiting, Indiana. She speaks of the conditions and details of her mother's migration from Czechoslovakia to the United States at the age of 15. Ms. Mores describes community and family life in Whiting, emphasizing the centrality of Roman Catholicism. In addition, she shares her beliefs regarding several supposed appearances of the Virgin Mary, the negative social impact of television, and environmental pollution in Whiting.
  Czechoslovakia; Ellis Island, New York; Fatima, Portugal; Lourdes, France; Catholicism; community life; family life; family values; Great Depression; immigration experiences; pollution; Television; St. John's Catholic Church; Standard Oil Company; Jakubovi; Bush, George, Sr.; Grenchik, Steven; Mores, Matthew; Sagan, Rose; Truman, Harry S.; Ustanik, Agnes
- Novosel, Joseph, Jr., October 15, 1990; 91-003; Dabertin, David; 33 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 73 minutes; index
  Joseph Novosel, Jr., born on November 17, 1960, discusses his Yugoslavian family background, his parents and family, and his youth and adult life in Whiting, Indiana. He speaks of the air and water pollution that occurred in Whiting as a result of heavy industry there, as well as his participation in the United Citizens Association to prevent further environmental pollution. He discusses and describes his education, career, community life, political beliefs, and the local economy.
  construction worker; engineer; Gary, Indiana; Hammond, Indiana; Dance Land fire; ethnic diversity; family values; local economy; pollution; racism; World War II; Midwest Limousine Corporation; United Citizens Association; Reagan, Ronald Wilson
- Novosel, Joseph, Sr., October 15, 1990; 91-002; Dabertin, David; 38 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 120 minutes; index
  Joseph Novosel, Sr., born on March 15, 1924, speaks of his parents, who emigrated from Croatia/Yugoslavia, and his youth in Whiting, Indiana. He discusses his participation in Boy Scouts, hunting, and fishing as a boy, as well as his memories of Prohibition, bootlegging, and a suicidal boarder who lived with his family for a time. In addition, he speaks of his attempts to enter military service in World War II, his career as an electrician, labor unions, and the area's economy and politics.
  electrician; Croatia; George Lake, Indiana; Wolf Lake, Indiana; Yugoslavia; 1955 Standard Oil fire; community life; ethnic diversity; family values; fishing; hunting; Jewish businesses; local economy; local politics; morals; Prohibition; religious divisions; unions; World War II; Standard Oil Company; Klodischitz, Steven
- Obermiller, William, January 17, 1991; 91-012; Klemm, Verda; 17 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 47 minutes; index; photo of interviewee, 9 articles about interviewee, Whiting Historical Society newsletter
  William Obermiller, born on June 22, 1923, recalls his childhood and life with his parents in Whiting, Indiana. A attorney and judge with experience in naval intelligence in World War II and the Korean War, Mr. Obermiller discusses his Catholic upbringing, the values he retains from his parents and his religion, and his application of those values through civic activities and voluntarism. In addition, he speaks of his wife and daughters and the impact television has had on the culture and speed of communication in the United States. Mr. Obermiller also remembers such events as the Pearl Harbor attack and the big Standard Oil fire in 1955.
  attorney; judge; naval intelligence officer; Taiwan; 1955 Standard Oil fire; Catholicism; family values; Television; World War II; Carmelite Home for Girls; Standard Oil Company; Obermiller, Anne
- Odlivak, Albert, July 29, 1991; 91-043; Klemm, Verda; 18 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 48 minutes; index
  Albert Odlivak, born on February 19, 1930, discusses the happiness of his childhood and adult life in Whiting, Indiana, the disciplined upbringing and family values he received from his parents, and the importance of the Greek Catholic church in his life. He emphasizes the value of the work ethic of his parents' generation and the importance of education, recalling his own years in Whiting's public elementary and high schools. In addition, Mr. Odlivak speaks of his memories of World War II and the Vietnam War, the changing aspect of local employment, and the rebirth of his love of drawing and painting.
  city water department superintedent; Education; family values; local employment; painting; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; work ethic; World War II; Standard Oil Company
- Palko, Ann; Badnarik, Elaine, April 30, 1992; 91-166; Bodnar, John; 64 pages; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 130 minutes; index; brief history of Whiting, Indiana
  Ann Palko, born in 1913, and Elaine Badnarik, born in 1934, each discuss the story of their antecedents' emigration to the United States from Slovakia, then part of Austria-Hungary. They speak of their youths in Hegewisch, Illinois, the process of Americanization as evidenced by family photographs, family values, and the importance of Catholicism in community life. Ms. Badnarik reveals her interest in genealogical research by relating many stories of her family and ancestors, both in Slovakia and America. Ms. Palko speaks of her work at Standard Oil, while Ms. Badnarik discusses being employed at Republic Steel. Both women emphasize generational differences in the Whiting community, including a lack of religious and traditional values in youth.
  Austria-Hungary; Hegewisch, Illinois; Orava, Czechoslovakia; Americanization; Catholicism; cultural traditions; discrimination; family values; Fourth of July; Great Depression; immigrants; local controversy; Rosary clubs; Whiting centennial; World War II; Daughters of Isabella; Immaculate Conception Catholic Church; Republic Steel; St. John's Catholic Church; St. Theresa Ladies' Parish Club; Standard Oil Company; Grenchik; Gima, Mary Cerep; Gima, Michael; Kennedy, John Fitzgerald; Rajcany, Benedict; Palko, Andro
- Plemons, Frank; Plemons, Joyce; Collins, Carol, May 15, 1991; 91-030; Berry, Chad; 51 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 78 minutes; index
  Frank Plemons, born on April 12, 1929, his wife, Joyce Plemons, born on October 29, 1938, and Carol Collins, born on April 14, 1948, discuss their background, families, and youth in Tennessee and their move to Whiting, Indiana to find jobs. They speak of the discrimination they experienced as Southerners in a primarily eastern European ethnic area. In addition, they stressed generational differences in family values, family size, and the degree of materialism, as well as discussing the best and largest employers in Whiting.
  Lenoir City, Tennessee; cost of living; discrimination; electricity; ethnic diversity; family size; family values; materialism; regional differences; technological changes; unions; work ethic; working conditions; Inland Steel; Lever Brothers; U.S. Steel; Plemons, Gary
- Pukac, Michael; Pukac, Julia, March 2, 1992; 91-153; Bodnar, John; 66 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 103 minutes; index
  Michael Pukac, born on November 15, 1922, and his wife Julia, born on February 26, 1922, recall their respective childhoods and adult lives in Whiting, Indiana. They discuss their employment histories, citing the importance of such major employers as AMOCO/Standard Oil and Lever Brothers, and the changes brought about by labor unions. The couple speaks of generational religious differences. The Pukacs also describe the benefits of living in their Arizona retirement community, as opposed to Whiting. In addition, they comment on minority job quotas at AMOCO, the 1955 Standard Oil fire, and the problems faced by the local community in Whiting.
  travel agent; Czechoslovakia; Robertsdale, Indiana; Sun City, Arizona; 1955 Standard Oil fire; Americanization; Catholicism; community life; Great Depression; minority groups; political party affiliation; pollution; religious philosophy; retirement; unions; Whiting city disrepair; World War II; AMOCO; Congress of Industrial Organizations; Standard Oil Company
- Saliga, George J., August 14, 1991; 91-045; Bodnar, John; 21 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 53 minutes; index
  George J. Saliga discusses his family history, Czechoslovakian heritage, and early life in Whiting, Indiana in this interview. He speaks of his work at Standard Oil Company and of his service in Italy and northern Africa in World War II. In addition, Mr. Saliga speaks of his time in Father Lach's band, playing at Carnegie Hall, and touring Europe with the band in the late nineteen thirties.
  ethnic diversity; Father Lach's band; mortar shells; unions; World War II; Dance Land; Immaculate Conception Catholic Church; Standard Oil Company; Losinski, Adam
- Sandrick, James, January 23, 1991; 91-018; Dabertin, David; 30 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 68 minutes; index
  James Sandrick, born on May 3, 1943, describes his youth in Robertsdale, Indiana, the local neighborhood, local employers, and the values he learned from his parents. He discusses one of his most important memories, Whiting's centennial celebration, and also speaks of Whiting's renowned annual Fourth of July parade. Mr. Sandrick talks about class distinctions in Whiting society and neighborhoods, as well as local air and water pollution, and the quality of local schools.
  insurance agent; Chicago, Illinois; Gary, Indiana; Hammond, Indiana; Robertsdale, Indiana; 1955 Standard Oil fire; family values; Fourth of July; local real estate; local schools; political party affiliation; pollution; social classes; steel mills; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; Whiting centennial; Standard Oil Company; Star Theater
- Scully, Anne V. "Peg", January 24, 1991; 91-015; Dabertin, David; 43 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 96 minutes; index
  Anne V. "Peg" Scully, born on July 12, 1905, describes her family, her childhood and adult life in Whiting, Indiana, and her employment history. She discusses her father's tavern, its demise during Prohibition, her days as a flapper, and Al Capone's gang activities in Whiting. In addition, she recalls the old movie theaters in Whiting and some home remedies used during her childhood.
  Hammond, Indiana; Stiglitz Park, Indiana; 1955 Standard Oil fire; Americanization; Capone gang; Education; flappers; home remedies; movie theaters; Prohibition; St. John's Catholic Church; Standard Oil Company
- Semancik, Lillian, November 2, 1992; 91-170; Orr, Lisa; 14 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 50 minutes; index
  Lillian Semancik discusses her Slovakian heritage, her Slovakian immigrant parents, and her childhood and adult life in Whiting, Indiana. She compares the cost of living in her youth to that of the present day, and describes the closeness of the Slovak community in Whiting. In addition, she speaks of the death of her father from pneumonia, before the advent of antibiotics, when she was still a child.
  cost of living; Slovak community
- Slack, Christopher; Slack, Esther, April 7, 1992; 91-163; Berry, Chad; 61 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 94 minutes; index
  Christopher Slack, and his wife, Esther Slack, who was born in 1964, describe their lives and respective families in Whiting, Indiana. Mrs. Slack describes growing up as a Mexican American in Whiting, while Mr. Slack describes his own Slovak family history and his traditional perception of gender roles. Also discussed are the primary employers in Whiting, family values, and generational differences with regard to activities of youth. They comment on the changing demographics of the Whiting community, as well as the increase in local crime.
  East Chicago, Illinois; alcohol; Catholicism; community life; Education; ethnic diversity; family values; Fourth of July; gender roles; local airport; local crime; local politics; marijuana; Mexican-Americans; Standard Oil Company
- Sotak, David, February 25, 1992; 91-149; Berry, Chad; 29 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 66 minutes; index
  David Sotak discusses his childhood and adult life in Whiting, Indiana, describing it as a "closed community" where all long-time residents know each other. He speaks of the values he learned from his parents and the changes in employment conditions and job security in Whiting. In addition, he comments on his memories of the nineteen sixties and the hippie movement in Whiting.
  family values; job security; local employment; materialism; nineteen sixties; work ethic; Clark High School; Standard Oil Company
- Sotak, Joseph J., November 6, 1991; 91-144; Bodnar, John; 46 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 108 minutes; index
  Born on February 9, 1914, Joseph J. Sotak discusses his years as a worker at Standard Oil and as a leader of the labor union. A professional basketball player in his youth and a member of the Coast Guard during World War II, Mr. Sotak speaks of the changes in unionization at Standard Oil Company over the years and of the repercussions of the fire in 1955 at Standard Oil. In addition, he shares his opinion of the newer generation of workers, including Mexican-Americans.
  1955 Standard Oil fire; divorce; labor strikes; Mexican-Americans; prejudice; professional basketball; racial diversity; riveting; still cleaning; unions; welding; World War II; AFL-CIO; AMOCO; Oil Chemical and Atomic Workers Union; Standard Oil Company; Endres, Art
- Stawitcke, Beatrice H., February 13, 1992; 91-158; Dabertin, David; 29 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 70 minutes; index
  Born on February 26, 1913, Beatrice H. Stawitcke relates details about her ancestry, her parents and childhood in Whiting, Indiana, and her employment history as a pianist, beginning in the years of the Great Depression. She recalls the community's immediate reactions to the 1955 fire at Standard Oil Company, and the repercussions of that explosion. In addition, Mrs. Stawitcke describes the increase in immorality she perceives to have taken place, beginning in the post-World War II era.
  pianist; 1955 Standard Oil fire; Andrews Sisters; community life; ethnic diversity; Fourth of July; Major Bowles Amateur Hour; musicians' union; religious beliefs; World War I; World War II; AFL; Dance Land; Whiting Flower Shop; Ahlgren, Oscar
- Tokarz, Dorothy; Tokarz, Edward, March 2, 1992; 91-150; Bodnar, John; 59 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 113 minutes; index
  Edward Tokarz, born on August 15, 1916, and his wife, Dorothy Tokarz, born on February 2, 1922, recall their respective childhoods, parents, Eastern European ethnic backgrounds, and adult lives in Whiting, Indiana. Mr. Tokarz speaks of his years as an employee of Standard Oil Company, describing his memories and the repercussions of the explosion and fire at Standard Oil in 1955. The couple recalls how they met, and comment on the importance of prayer in their daily lives, the pollution in and around Whiting, and generational differences in worker motivation, crime rates, drug abuse, and divorce.
  George Lake, Indiana; Sun City, Arizona; 1955 Standard Oil fire; credit cards; divorce; George Lake landfill; layoffs; local crime; pollution; prayer; still cleaning; substance abuse; Television; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; World War II; AMOCO; Congress of Industrial Organizations; Standard Oil Company
- Uñate, Romualdo; Uñate, Elva, January 20, 1993; 91-174; Wolford, John; 73 pages; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 150 minutes; index
  Romualdo Uñate, born on October 28, 1929, and his wife Elva Uñate, born on December 28, 1933, discuss their respective childhoods and youths in Mexico, their parents, siblings, and upbringing there, and their move to Whiting, Indiana, soon after their marriage in 1953. They speak of cultural and generational differences with regard to gender roles and work ethic. In addition, the Uñates emphasize the importance of Catholicism in their lives and the fact that education was a high priority for their children. Mr. Uñate also comments on his years working for Inland Steel, labor union activity there, and the problem of local unemployment.
  East Chicago, Illinois; Zaragoza, Coahuila, Mexico; Catholic school tuition; Catholicism; Education; gender roles; local employment; Mexican-Americans; unions; Inland Steel
- Villalon, Hector, December 19, 1992; 91-172; Wolford, John; 101 pages; 4 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 195 minutes; index; 4 photographs of interviewee, interview notes, interviewee's genealogy
  Born on January 13, 1945, Hector Villalon relates details about his Texas childhood, his parents, his early entrance into the United States Army, and his status as a champion boxer while stationed in Germany. He also summarizes his job history, from newspaper delivery routes as a child, to a high level security position working for Dr. Wernher Von Braun, to his years and promotions at AMOCO. He comments on the importance of Roman Catholicism in his life and of the emphasis he placed on education for his children. In addition, Mr. Villalon discusses the ethnic diversity of Whiting, Indiana, urban growth, in general, and the generational differences that have resulted in a decrease in the degree of parental supervision of their children and an increase in drug abuse.
  Brownsville, Texas; Cicero, Illinois; Mexico; Catholicism; ethnic diversity; family values; Iwo Jima battle; John F. Kennedy assassination; Mexican-Americans; photography; substance abuse; unions; urban changes; work ethic; AMOCO; Bishop Knoll Institute; Ballet Folklorico; United States Army; Block, Harlon H.; Pavlo, Andy; Perot, Ross; Sullivan, Gene; Von Braun, Wernher
- Weller, Dennis, May 14, 1991; 91-028; Berry, Chad; 39 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 79 minutes; index
  Dennis Weller, born on May 25, 1951, describes his childhood and adult life in Whiting, Indiana, citing major generational differences in the areas of community spirit, local demographics, and standards of property upkeep. He discusses his employment history, beginning at Youngstown Sheet and Tube, and culminating as Whiting chief of police. In addition, Mr. Weller comments on the job security associated with various employers, his memories of meeting his wife, and on the importance of local politics.
  police officer; community pride; family values; job security; local politics; pheasant hunting; political party affiliation; Religion; unions; Youngstown Sheet and Tube
- Westerfield, Anna, April 7, 1992; 91-159; Berry, Chad; 43 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 74 minutes; index
  Anna Westerfield, born on June 7, 1965, joined by her mother, discuss the differences apparent in their lives between southern rural and northern urban cultures. Christian values, the Baptist faith, and prayer are emphasized as important in the lives of both women, though their description of southern culture included several examples of racism. In addition, Ms. Westerfield spoke of her employment history and her appreciation of a more urban life-style.
  Kentucky; Baptist faith; family values; gender roles; high school education; interracial marriages; prayer; racism; women workers
- Westerfield, Herschel; Westerfield, Beverly, July 26, 1991; 91-042; Berry, Chad; 44 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 90 minutes; index